<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ Hibernate, Relational Persistence for Idiomatic Java
  ~
  ~ Copyright (c) 2008, Red Hat Middleware LLC or third-party contributors as
  ~ indicated by the @author tags or express copyright attribution
  ~ statements applied by the authors.  All third-party contributions are
  ~ distributed under license by Red Hat Middleware LLC.
  ~
  ~ This copyrighted material is made available to anyone wishing to use, modify,
  ~ copy, or redistribute it subject to the terms and conditions of the GNU
  ~ Lesser General Public License, as published by the Free Software Foundation.
  ~
  ~ This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY
  ~ or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ for more details.
  ~
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ along with this distribution; if not, write to:
  ~ Free Software Foundation, Inc.
  ~ 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor
  ~ Boston, MA  02110-1301  USA
  -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../HIBERNATE_-_Relational_Persistence_for_Idiomatic_Java.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;

]>

<preface id="preface">
    <title>Preface</title>

    <para>
        Working with object-oriented software and a relational database can be cumbersome
        and time consuming in today's enterprise environments. Hibernate is an Object/Relational
        Mapping tool for Java environments. The term Object/Relational Mapping (ORM) refers to
        the technique of mapping a data representation from an object model to a relational
        data model with a SQL-based schema.
    </para>

    <para>
        Hibernate not only takes care of the mapping from Java classes to
        database tables (and from Java data types to SQL data types), but also provides data
        query and retrieval facilities. It can also significantly reduce development time otherwise
        spent with manual data handling in SQL and JDBC.
    </para>

    <para>
        Hibernate's goal is to relieve the developer from 95 percent of common data persistence
        related programming tasks. Hibernate may not be the best solution for data-centric
        applications that only use stored-procedures to implement the business logic in the
        database, it is most useful with object-oriented domain models and business logic in
        the Java-based middle-tier. However, Hibernate can certainly help you to remove or
        encapsulate vendor-specific SQL code and will help with the common task of result set
        translation from a tabular representation to a graph of objects.
    </para>

    <para>
        If you are new to Hibernate and Object/Relational Mapping or even Java,
        please follow these steps:
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Read <xref linkend="tutorial"/> for a tutorial with step-by-step
                instructions. The source code for the tutorial is included in the
                distribution in the <literal>doc/reference/tutorial/</literal>
                directory.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Read <xref linkend="architecture"/> to understand the environments where
                Hibernate can be used.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                View the <literal>eg/</literal> directory in the Hibernate
                distribution. It contains a simple standalone application. Copy your
                JDBC driver to the <literal>lib/</literal> directory and edit
                <literal>etc/hibernate.properties</literal>, specifying correct values for
                your database. From a command prompt in the distribution directory,
                type <literal>ant eg</literal> (using Ant), or under Windows, type
                <literal>build eg</literal>.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Use this reference documentation as your primary source of
                information.  Consider reading <biblioref linkend="biblio-JPwH"/>
                if you need more help with application design, or if you prefer
                a step-by-step tutorial. Also visit
                <ulink url="http://caveatemptor.hibernate.org"/> and download
                the example application from <biblioref linkend="biblio-JPwH"/>.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                FAQs are answered on the Hibernate website.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Links to third party demos, examples, and tutorials are maintained
                on the Hibernate website.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                The Community Area on the Hibernate website is a good resource for
                design patterns and various integration solutions (Tomcat, JBoss AS,
                Struts, EJB, etc.).
            </para>
        </listitem>
     </orderedlist>

     <para>
         If you have questions, use the user forum linked on the Hibernate website. We also
         provide a JIRA issue tracking system for bug reports and feature requests. If you
         are interested in the development of Hibernate, join the developer mailing list. If
         you are interested in translating this documentation into your language, contact us
         on the developer mailing list.
     </para>

     <para>
         Commercial development support, production support, and training for Hibernate is
         available through JBoss Inc. (see http://www.hibernate.org/SupportTraining/).
         Hibernate is a Professional Open Source project and a critical component of the
         JBoss Enterprise Middleware System (JEMS) suite of products.
     </para>

</preface>
