<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>

<!--
  ~ Hibernate, Relational Persistence for Idiomatic Java
  ~
  ~ License: GNU Lesser General Public License (LGPL), version 2.1 or later.
  ~ See the lgpl.txt file in the root directory or <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl-2.1.html>.
  -->
<chapter xml:id="fetching"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Fetching</title>

    <!-- todo : document special fetching considerations such as batch fetching, subselect fetching and extra laziness -->
    <!-- todo : document "dynamic fetching via JPA entity graphs" -->
    <!-- todo : list out the default fetching strategies by association type (JPA); recommend all lazy; allow users to override the to-one default (add jira) -->

    <para>
        Fetching, essentially, is the process of grabbing data from the database and making it available to the
        application.  Tuning how an application does fetching is one of the biggest factors in determining how an
        application will perform.  Fetching too much data, in terms of width (values/columns) and/or
        depth (results/rows), adds unnecessary overhead in terms of both JDBC communication and ResultSet processing.
        Fetching too little data causes additional fetches to be needed.  Tuning how an application
        fetches data presents a great opportunity to influence the application's overall performance.
    </para>

    <section>
        <title>The basics</title>

        <para>
            The concept of fetching breaks down into two different questions.
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        When should the data be fetched?  Now?  Later?
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        How should the data be fetched?
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <note>
            <para>
                "now" is generally termed <phrase>eager</phrase> or <phrase>immediate</phrase>.  "later" is
                generally termed <phrase>lazy</phrase> or <phrase>delayed</phrase>.
            </para>
        </note>

        <para>
            There are a number of scopes for defining fetching:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>static</emphasis> - Static definition of fetching strategies is done in the
                        mappings.  The statically-defined fetch strategies is used in the absence of any dynamically
                        defined strategies <footnote><para>Except in the case of HQL/JPQL; see xyz</para></footnote>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>dynamic</emphasis> (sometimes referred to as runtime) - Dynamic definition is
                        really use-case centric.  There are 2 main ways to define dynamic fetching:
                    </para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <emphasis>fetch profiles</emphasis> - defined in mappings, but can be
                                enabled/disabled on the Session.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                HQL/JPQL and both Hibernate and JPA Criteria queries have the ability to specify
                                fetching, specific to said query.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Starting in Hibernate 4.2 (JPA 2.1) you can also use JPA EntityGraphs.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <variablelist>
            <title>The strategies</title>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>SELECT</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Performs a separate SQL select to load the data.  This can either be EAGER (the second select
                        is issued immediately) or LAZY (the second select is delayed until the data is needed).  This
                        is the strategy generally termed <phrase>N+1</phrase>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>JOIN</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Inherently an EAGER style of fetching.  The data to be fetched is obtained through the use of
                        an SQL join.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>BATCH</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Performs a separate SQL select to load a number of related data items using an
                        IN-restriction as part of the SQL WHERE-clause based on a batch size.  Again, this can either
                        be EAGER (the second select is issued immediately) or LAZY (the second select is delayed until
                        the data is needed).
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>SUBSELECT</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Performs a separate SQL select to load associated data based on the SQL restriction used to
                        load the owner.  Again, this can either be EAGER (the second select is issued immediately)
                        or LAZY (the second select is delayed until the data is needed).
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Applying fetch strategies</title>

        <para>
            Let's consider these topics as it relates to an simple domain model and a few use cases.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Sample domain model</title>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/Employee.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/Department.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/Project.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>

        <important>
            <para>
                The Hibernate recommendation is to statically mark all associations lazy and to use dynamic fetching
                strategies for eagerness.  This is unfortunately at odds with the JPA specification which defines that
                all one-to-one and many-to-one associations should be eagerly fetched by default.  Hibernate, as a JPA
                provider, honors that default.
            </para>
        </important>

        <section>
            <title>No fetching</title>
            <subtitle>The login use-case</subtitle>
            <para>
                For the first use case, consider the application's login process for an Employee.  Lets assume that
                login only requires access to the Employee information, not Project nor Department information.
            </para>

            <example>
                <title>No fetching example</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/Login.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>

            <para>
                In this example, the application gets the Employee data.  However, because all associations from
                Employee are declared as LAZY (JPA defines the default for collections as LAZY) no other data is
                fetched.
            </para>

            <para>
                If the login process does not need access to the Employee information specifically, another
                fetching optimization here would be to limit the width of the query results.
            </para>

            <example>
                <title>No fetching (scalar) example</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/LoginScalar.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Dynamic fetching via queries</title>
            <subtitle>The projects for an employee use-case</subtitle>

            <para>
                For the second use case, consider a screen displaying the Projects for an Employee.  Certainly access
                to the Employee is needed, as is the collection of Projects for that Employee.  Information
                about Departments, other Employees or other Projects is not needed.
            </para>

            <example>
                <title>Dynamic query fetching example</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/ProjectsForAnEmployeeHql.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/ProjectsForAnEmployeeCriteria.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>

            <para>
                In this example we have an Employee and their Projects loaded in a single query shown both as an HQL
                query and a JPA Criteria query.  In both cases, this resolves to exactly one database query to get all
                that information.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Dynamic fetching via profiles</title>
            <subtitle>The projects for an employee use-case using natural-id</subtitle>

            <para>
                Suppose we wanted to leverage loading by natural-id to obtain the Employee information in the
                "projects for and employee" use-case.  Loading by natural-id uses the statically defined fetching
                strategies, but does not expose a means to define load-specific fetching.  So we would leverage a
                fetch profile.
            </para>

            <example>
                <title>Fetch profile example</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/FetchOverrides.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/ProjectsForAnEmployeeFetchProfile.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>

            <para>
                Here the Employee is obtained by natural-id lookup and the Employee's Project data is fetched eagerly.
                If the Employee data is resolved from cache, the Project data is resolved on its own.  However,
                if the Employee data is not resolved in cache, the Employee and Project data is resolved in one
                SQL query via join as we saw above.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

</chapter>