<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>

<!--
  ~ Hibernate, Relational Persistence for Idiomatic Java
  ~
  ~ License: GNU Lesser General Public License (LGPL), version 2.1 or later.
  ~ See the lgpl.txt file in the root directory or <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl-2.1.html>.
  -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <title>HQL and JPQL</title>

    <para>
        The Hibernate Query Language (HQL) and Java Persistence Query Language (JPQL) are both object model
        focused query languages similar in nature to SQL.  JPQL is a heavily-inspired-by subset of HQL.  A JPQL
        query is always a valid HQL query, the reverse is not true however.
    </para>

    <para>
        Both HQL and JPQL are non-type-safe ways to perform query operations.  Criteria queries offer a
        type-safe approach to querying.  See <xref linkend="query-criteria" /> for more information.
    </para>

    <section>
        <title>Case Sensitivity</title>

        <para>
            With the exception of names of Java classes and properties, queries are case-insensitive.
            So <literal>SeLeCT</literal> is the same as <literal>sELEct</literal> is the same as
            <literal>SELECT</literal>, but
            <literal>org.hibernate.eg.FOO</literal> and <literal>org.hibernate.eg.Foo</literal> are different, as are
            <literal>foo.barSet</literal> and <literal>foo.BARSET</literal>.
        </para>

        <note>
            <para>
                This documentation uses lowercase keywords as convention in examples.
            </para>
        </note>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Statement types</title>
        <para>
            Both HQL and JPQL allow <literal>SELECT</literal>, <literal>UPDATE</literal> and <literal>DELETE</literal>
            statements to be performed.  HQL additionally allows <literal>INSERT</literal> statements, in a form
            similar to a SQL <literal>INSERT-SELECT</literal>.
        </para>

        <important>
            <para>
                Care should be taken as to when a <literal>UPDATE</literal> or <literal>DELETE</literal> statement is
                executed.
            </para>
            <blockquote>
                <attribution><citetitle pubwork="section">Section 4.10 of the JPA 2.0 Specification</citetitle></attribution>
                <para>
                    Caution should be used when executing bulk update or delete operations because they may result in
                    inconsistencies between the database and the entities in the active persistence context. In general, bulk
                    update and delete operations should only be performed within a transaction in a new persistence con-
                    text or before fetching or accessing entities whose state might be affected by such operations.
                </para>
            </blockquote>
        </important>

        <section>
            <title>Select statements</title>
            <para>
                The BNF for <literal>SELECT</literal> statements in HQL is:
            </para>
            <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/statement_select_bnf.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <para>
                The simplest possible HQL <literal>SELECT</literal> statement is of the form:
            </para>
            <programlisting>from com.acme.Cat</programlisting>
            <para>
                The select statement in JPQL is exactly the same as for HQL except that JPQL requires a
                <literal>select_clause</literal>, whereas HQL does not.  Even though HQL does not require the presence
                of a <literal>select_clause</literal>, it is generally good practice to include one.  For simple queries
                the intent is clear and so the intended result of the <literal>select_clause</literal> is east to
                infer.  But on more complex queries that is not always the case.  It is usually better to explicitly
                specify intent.  Hibernate does not actually enforce that a <literal>select_clause</literal> be present
                even when parsing JPQL queries, however applications interested in JPA portability should take heed of
                this.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Update statements</title>
            <para>
                The BNF for <literal>UPDATE</literal> statements is the same in HQL and JPQL:
            </para>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/statement_update_bnf.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <para>
                <literal>UPDATE</literal> statements, by default, do not effect the <literal>version</literal>
                or the <literal>timestamp</literal> attribute values for the affected entities. However,
                you can force Hibernate to set the <literal>version</literal> or <literal>timestamp</literal> attribute
                values through the use of a <literal>versioned update</literal>.  This is achieved by adding the
                <literal>VERSIONED</literal> keyword after the <literal>UPDATE</literal> keyword.  Note, however, that
                this is a Hibernate specific feature and will not work in a portable manner.  Custom version types,
                <interfacename>org.hibernate.usertype.UserVersionType</interfacename>, are not allowed in conjunction
                with a <literal>update versioned</literal> statement.
            </para>
            <para>
                An <literal>UPDATE</literal> statement is executed using the <methodname>executeUpdate</methodname>
                of either <interfacename>org.hibernate.Query</interfacename> or
                <interfacename>javax.persistence.Query</interfacename>.  The method is named for those familiar with
                the JDBC <methodname>executeUpdate</methodname> on <interfacename>java.sql.PreparedStatement</interfacename>.
                The <literal>int</literal> value returned by the <methodname>executeUpdate()</methodname> method
                indicates the number of entities effected by the operation.  This may or may not correlate to the number
                of rows effected in the database.  An HQL bulk operation might result in multiple actual SQL statements
                being executed (for joined-subclass, for example).  The returned number indicates the number of actual
                entities affected by the statement.  Using a JOINED inheritance hierarchy, a delete against one of the
                subclasses may actually result in deletes against not just the table to which that subclass is mapped,
                but also the "root" table and tables <quote>in between</quote>
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Example UPDATE query statements</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/statement_update_example_hql.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/statement_update_example_jpql.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/statement_update_example_hql_versioned.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
        </section>

        <important>
            <para>
                Neither <literal>UPDATE</literal> nor <literal>DELETE</literal> statements are allowed to
                result in what is called an implicit join.  Their form already disallows explicit joins.
            </para>
        </important>

        <section>
            <title>Delete statements</title>
            <para>
                The BNF for <literal>DELETE</literal> statements is the same in HQL and JPQL:
            </para>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/statement_delete_bnf.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <para>
                A <literal>DELETE</literal> statement is also executed using the <methodname>executeUpdate</methodname>
                method of either <interfacename>org.hibernate.Query</interfacename> or
                <interfacename>javax.persistence.Query</interfacename>.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Insert statements</title>
            <para>
                HQL adds the ability to define <literal>INSERT</literal> statements as well.  There is no JPQL
                equivalent to this.  The BNF for an HQL <literal>INSERT</literal> statement is:
            </para>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/statement_insert_bnf.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <para>
                The <literal>attribute_list</literal> is analogous to the <literal>column specification</literal> in the
                SQL <literal>INSERT</literal> statement.  For entities involved in mapped inheritance, only attributes
                directly defined on the named entity can be used in the <literal>attribute_list</literal>.  Superclass
                properties are not allowed and subclass properties do not make sense.  In other words,
                <literal>INSERT</literal> statements are inherently non-polymorphic.
            </para>
            <para>
                <literal>select_statement</literal> can be any valid HQL select query, with the caveat that the return
                types must match the types expected by the insert.  Currently, this is checked during query
                compilation rather than allowing the check to relegate to the database.  This may cause problems
                between Hibernate Types which are <emphasis>equivalent</emphasis> as opposed to
                <emphasis>equal</emphasis>.  For example, this might cause lead to issues with mismatches between an
                attribute mapped as a <classname>org.hibernate.type.DateType</classname> and an attribute defined as
                a <classname>org.hibernate.type.TimestampType</classname>, even though the database might not make a
                distinction or might be able to handle the conversion.
            </para>
            <para>
                For the id attribute, the insert statement gives you two options.  You can either explicitly specify
                the id property in the <literal>attribute_list</literal>, in which case its value is taken from the
                corresponding select expression, or omit it from the <literal>attribute_list</literal> in which case a
                generated value is used.  This latter option is only available when using id generators that operate
                <quote>in the database</quote>; attempting to use this option with any <quote>in memory</quote> type
                generators will cause an exception during parsing.
            </para>
            <para>
                For optimistic locking attributes, the insert statement again gives you two options.  You can either
                specify the attribute in the <literal>attribute_list</literal> in which case its value is taken from
                the corresponding select expressions, or omit it from the <literal>attribute_list</literal> in which
                case the <literal>seed value</literal> defined by the corresponding
                <interfacename>org.hibernate.type.VersionType</interfacename> is used.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Example INSERT query statements</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/statement_insert_example_named_id.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="ql-from-clause">
        <title>The <literal>FROM</literal> clause</title>
        <para>
            The <literal>FROM</literal> clause is responsible defining the scope of object model types available to
            the rest of the query.  It also is responsible for defining all the <quote>identification variables</quote>
            available to the rest of the query.
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>Identification variables</title>
            <para>
                Identification variables are often referred to as aliases.  References to object model classes
                in the FROM clause can be associated with an identification variable that can then be used to
                refer to that type thoughout the rest of the query.
            </para>
            <para>
                In most cases declaring an identification variable is optional, though it is usually good practice to
                declare them.
            </para>
            <para>
                An identification variable must follow the rules for Java identifier validity.
            </para>
            <para>
                According to JPQL, identification variables must be treated as case insensitive.  Good practice
                says you should use the same case throughout a query to refer to a given identification variable.  In
                other words, JPQL says they <emphasis>can be</emphasis> case insensitive and so Hibernate must
                be able to treat them as such, but this does not make it good practice.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Root entity references</title>
            <para>
                A root entity reference, or what JPA calls a <literal>range variable declaration</literal>, is
                specifically a reference to a mapped entity type from the application.  It cannot name component/
                embeddable types.  And associations, including collections, are handled in a different manner
                discussed later.
            </para>
            <para>
                The BNF for a root entity reference is:
            </para>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/root_entity_ref_bnf.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <example id="ql-simple-query-ex">
                <title>Simple query example</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/simplest_query.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                We see that the query is defining a root entity reference to the <classname>com.acme.Cat</classname>
                object model type.  Additionally, it declares an alias of <literal>c</literal> to that
                <classname>com.acme.Cat</classname> reference; this is the identification variable.
            </para>
            <para>
                Usually the root entity reference just names the <literal>entity name</literal> rather than the
                entity class FQN.  By default the entity name is the unqualified entity class name,
                here <literal>Cat</literal>
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Simple query using entity name for root entity reference</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/simplest_query2.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                Multiple root entity references can also be specified.  Even naming the same entity!
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Simple query using multiple root entity references</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/multiple_root_entity_ref_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/multiple_root_entity_ref_example2.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Explicit joins</title>
            <para>
                The <literal>FROM</literal> clause can also contain explicit relationship joins using the
                <literal>join</literal> keyword.  These joins can be either <literal>inner</literal>
                or <literal>left outer</literal> style joins.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Explicit inner join examples</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/join_example_explicit_inner.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <example>
                <title>Explicit left (outer) join examples</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/join_example_explicit_outer.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                An important use case for explicit joins is to define <literal>FETCH JOINS</literal> which override
                the laziness of the joined association.  As an example, given an entity named <classname>Customer</classname>
                with a collection-valued association named <literal>orders</literal>
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Fetch join example</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/join_example_fetch.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                As you can see from the example, a fetch join is specified by injecting the keyword <literal>fetch</literal>
                after the keyword <literal>join</literal>.  In the example, we used a left outer join because we want
                to return customers who have no orders also.  Inner joins can also be fetched.  But inner joins still
                filter.  In the example, using an inner join instead would have resulted in customers without any orders
                being filtered out of the result.
            </para>
            <important>
                <para>
                    Fetch joins are not valid in sub-queries.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Care should be taken when fetch joining a collection-valued association which is in any way further
                    restricted; the fetched collection will be restricted too!  For this reason it is usually considered
                    best practice to not assign an identification variable to fetched joins except for the purpose
                    of specifying nested fetch joins.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Fetch joins should not be used in paged queries (aka, <methodname>setFirstResult</methodname>/
                    <methodname>setMaxResults</methodname>).  Nor should they be used with the HQL
                    <methodname>scroll</methodname> or <methodname>iterate</methodname> features.
                </para>
            </important>
            <para>
                HQL also defines a <literal>WITH</literal> clause to qualify the join conditions.  Again, this is
                specific to HQL; JPQL does not define this feature.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>with-clause join example</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/join_example_with.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                The important distinction is that in the generated SQL the conditions of the
                <literal>with clause</literal> are made part of the <literal>on clause</literal> in the generated SQL
                as opposed to the other queries in this section where the HQL/JPQL conditions are made part of the
                <literal>where clause</literal> in the generated SQL.  The distinction in this specific example is
                probably not that significant.  The <literal>with clause</literal> is sometimes necessary in more
                complicated queries.
            </para>
            <para>
                Explicit joins may reference association or component/embedded attributes.  For further information
                about collection-valued association references, see <xref linkend="ql-collection-valued-associations"/>.
                In the case of component/embedded attributes, the join is simply logical and does not correlate to a
                physical (SQL) join.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Implicit joins (path expressions)</title>
            <para>
                Another means of adding to the scope of object model types available to the query is through the
                use of implicit joins, or path expressions.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Simple implicit join example</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/join_example_implicit.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                An implicit join always starts from an <literal>identification variable</literal>, followed by
                the navigation operator (.), followed by an attribute for the object model type referenced by the
                initial <literal>identification variable</literal>.  In the example, the initial
                <literal>identification variable</literal> is <literal>c</literal> which refers to the
                <classname>Customer</classname> entity.  The <literal>c.chiefExecutive</literal> reference then refers
                to the <methodname>chiefExecutive</methodname> attribute of the <classname>Customer</classname> entity.
                <methodname>chiefExecutive</methodname> is an association type so we further navigate to its
                <methodname>age</methodname> attribute.
            </para>
            <important>
                <para>
                    If the attribute represents an entity association (non-collection) or a component/embedded, that
                    reference can be further navigated.  Basic values and collection-valued associations cannot be
                    further navigated.
                </para>
            </important>
            <para>
                As shown in the example, implicit joins can appear outside the <literal>FROM clause</literal>.  However,
                they affect the <literal>FROM clause</literal>.  Implicit joins are always treated as inner joins.
                Multiple references to the same implicit join always refer to the same logical and physical (SQL) join.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Reused implicit join</title>
                <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/join_example_implicit_reused.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                Just as with explicit joins, implicit joins may reference association or component/embedded attributes.
                For further information about collection-valued association references, see
                <xref linkend="ql-collection-valued-associations"/>.  In the case of component/embedded attributes,
                the join is simply logical and does not correlate to a physical (SQL) join.  Unlike explicit joins,
                however, implicit joins may also reference basic state fields as long as the path expression ends
                there.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id="ql-collection-valued-associations">
            <title>Collection member references</title>
            <para>
                References to collection-valued associations actually refer to the <emphasis>values</emphasis> of
                that collection.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Collection references example</title>
                <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/collection_reference_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                In the example, the identification variable <literal>o</literal> actually refers to the object model
                type <classname>Order</classname> which is the type of the elements of the
                <methodname>Customer#orders</methodname> association.
            </para>
            <para>
                The example also shows the alternate syntax for specifying collection association joins using the
                <literal>IN</literal> syntax.  Both forms are equivalent.  Which form an application chooses to use is
                simply a matter of taste.
            </para>
            <section id="ql-collection-qualification">
                <title>Special case - qualified path expressions</title>
                <para>
                    We said earlier that collection-valued associations actually refer to the <emphasis>values</emphasis>
                    of that collection.  Based on the type of collection, there are also available a set of
                    explicit qualification expressions.
                </para>
                <example>
                    <title>Qualified collection references example</title>
                    <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/qualified_path_expressions_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                </example>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>VALUE</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Refers to the collection value.  Same as not specifying a qualifier.  Useful to
                                explicitly show intent.  Valid for any type of collection-valued reference.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>INDEX</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                According to HQL rules, this is valid for both Maps and Lists which specify a
                                <interfacename>javax.persistence.OrderColumn</interfacename> annotation to refer to
                                the Map key or the List position (aka the OrderColumn value).  JPQL however, reserves
                                this for use in the List case and adds <literal>KEY</literal> for the MAP case.
                                Applications interested in JPA provider portability should be aware of this
                                distinction.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>KEY</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Valid only for Maps.  Refers to the map's key.  If the key is itself an entity,
                                can be further navigated.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>ENTRY</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Only valid only for Maps.  Refers to the Map's logical
                                <interfacename>java.util.Map.Entry</interfacename> tuple (the combination  of its key
                                and value).  <literal>ENTRY</literal> is only valid as a terminal path and only valid
                                in the select clause.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
                <para>
                    See <xref linkend="ql-collection-expressions"/> for additional details on collection related
                    expressions.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Polymorphism</title>
            <para>
                HQL and JPQL queries are inherently polymorphic.
            </para>
            <programlisting>select p from Payment p</programlisting>
            <para>
                This query names the <classname>Payment</classname> entity explicitly.  However, all subclasses of
                <classname>Payment</classname> are also available to the query.  So if the
                <classname>CreditCardPayment</classname> entity and <classname>WireTransferPayment</classname> entity
                each extend from <classname>Payment</classname> all three types would be available to the query.  And
                the query would return instances of all three.
            </para>
            <note>
                <title>The logical extreme</title>
                <para>
                    The HQL query <literal>from java.lang.Object</literal> is totally valid!  It returns every
                    object of every type defined in your application. 
                </para>
            </note>
            <para>
                This can be altered by using either the
                <interfacename>org.hibernate.annotations.Polymorphism</interfacename> annotation (global, and
                Hibernate-specific) or limiting them using in the query itself using an entity type expression.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="ql-expressions">
        <title>Expressions</title>

        <para>
            Essentially expressions are references that resolve to basic or tuple values.
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>Identification variable</title>
            <para>
                See <xref linkend="ql-from-clause"/>.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Path expressions</title>
            <para>
                Again, see <xref linkend="ql-from-clause"/>.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Literals</title>
            <para>
                String literals are enclosed in single-quotes.  To escape a single-quote within a string literal, use
                double single-quotes.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>String literal examples</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/string_literals_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>

            <para>
                Numeric literals are allowed in a few different forms.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Numeric literal examples</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/numeric_literals_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                In the scientific notation form, the <literal>E</literal> is case insensitive.
            </para>
            <para>
                Specific typing can be achieved through the use of the same suffix approach specified by Java.  So,
                <literal>L</literal> denotes a long; <literal>D</literal> denotes a double; <literal>F</literal>
                denotes a float.  The actual suffix is case insensitive.
            </para>

            <para>
                The boolean literals are <literal>TRUE</literal> and <literal>FALSE</literal>, again case-insensitive.
            </para>

            <para>
                Enums can even be referenced as literals.  The fully-qualified enum class name must be used.  HQL
                can also handle constants in the same manner, though JPQL does not define that as supported.
            </para>

            <para>
                Entity names can also be used as literal.  See <xref linkend="ql-entity-type-exp"/>.
            </para>

            <para>
                Date/time literals can be specified using the JDBC escape syntax: <literal>{d 'yyyy-mm-dd'}</literal>
                for dates, <literal>{t 'hh:mm:ss'}</literal> for times and
                <literal>{ts 'yyyy-mm-dd hh:mm:ss[.millis]'}</literal> (millis optional) for timestamps.  These
                literals only work if you JDBC drivers supports them.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Parameters</title>
            <para>
                HQL supports all 3 of the following forms.  JPQL does not support the HQL-specific positional
                parameters notion.  It is good practice to not mix forms in a given query.
            </para>
            <section>
                <title>Named parameters</title>
                <para>
                    Named parameters are declared using a colon followed by an identifier -
                    <literal>:aNamedParameter</literal>.  The same named parameter can appear multiple times in a query.
                </para>
                <example>
                    <title>Named parameter examples</title>
                    <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/named_parameter_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                </example>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Positional (JPQL) parameters</title>
                <para>
                    JPQL-style positional parameters are declared using a question mark followed by an ordinal -
                    <literal>?1</literal>, <literal>?2</literal>.  The ordinals start with 1.  Just like with
                    named parameters, positional parameters can also appear multiple times in a query.
                </para>
                <example>
                    <title>Positional (JPQL) parameter examples</title>
                    <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/jpql_positional_parameter_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                </example>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Positional (HQL) parameters</title>
                <para>
                    HQL-style positional parameters follow JDBC positional parameter syntax.  They are declared using
                    <literal>?</literal> without a following ordinal.  There is no way to relate two such
                    positional parameters as being "the same" aside from binding the same value to each.
                </para>
                <para>
                    This form should be considered deprecated and may be removed in the near future.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Arithmetic</title>
            <para>
                Arithmetic operations also represent valid expressions.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Numeric arithmetic examples</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/arithmetic_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                The following rules apply to the result of arithmetic operations:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        If either of the operands is Double/double, the result is a Double;
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        else, if either of the operands is Float/float, the result is a Float;
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        else, if either operand is BigDecimal, the result is BigDecimal;
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        else, if either operand is BigInteger, the result is BigInteger (except for division, in
                        which case the result type is not further defined);
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        else, if either operand is Long/long, the result is Long (except for division, in
                        which case the result type is not further defined);
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        else, (the assumption being that both operands are of integral type) the result is Integer
                        (except for division, in which case the result type is not further defined);
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>
                Date arithmetic is also supported, albeit in a more limited fashion.  This is due partially to
                differences in database support and partially to the lack of support for <literal>INTERVAL</literal>
                definition in the query language itself.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Concatenation (operation)</title>
            <para>
                HQL defines a concatenation operator in addition to supporting the concatenation
                (<literal>CONCAT</literal>) function.  This is not defined by JPQL, so portable applications
                should avoid it use.  The concatenation operator is taken from the SQL concatenation operator -
                <literal>||</literal>.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Concatenation operation example</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/concat_op_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                See <xref linkend="ql-exp-functions"/> for details on the <literal>concat()</literal> function
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Aggregate functions</title>
            <para>
                Aggregate functions are also valid expressions in HQL and JPQL.  The semantic is the same as their
                SQL counterpart.  The supported aggregate functions are:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <literal>COUNT</literal> (including distinct/all qualifiers) - The result type is always Long.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <literal>AVG</literal> -  The result type is always Double.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <literal>MIN</literal> - The result type is the same as the argument type.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <literal>MAX</literal> - The result type is the same as the argument type.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <literal>SUM</literal> -  The result type of the <literal>avg()</literal> function depends on
                        the type of the values being averaged.  For integral values (other than BigInteger), the result
                        type is Long.  For floating point values (other than BigDecimal) the result type is Double.  For
                        BigInteger values, the result type is BigInteger.  For BigDecimal values, the result type is
                        BigDecimal.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <example>
                <title>Aggregate function examples</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/agg_func_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                Aggregations often appear with grouping.  For information on grouping see <xref linkend="ql-grouping"/>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="ql-exp-functions">
            <title>Scalar functions</title>
            <para>
                Both HQL and JPQL define some standard functions that are available regardless of the underlying 
                database in use.  HQL can also understand additional functions defined by the Dialect as well as the 
                application.
            </para>

            <section>
                <title>Standardized functions - JPQL</title>
                <para>
                    Here are the list of functions defined as supported by JPQL.  Applications interested in remaining
                    portable between JPA providers should stick to these functions.
                </para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>CONCAT</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                String concatenation function.  Variable argument length of 2 or more string values
                                to be concatenated together.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>SUBSTRING</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Extracts a portion of a string value.
                            </para>
                            <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/substring_bnf.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                            <para>
                                The second argument denotes the starting position.  The third (optional) argument
                                denotes the length.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>UPPER</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Upper cases the specified string
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>LOWER</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Lower cases the specified string
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>TRIM</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Follows the semantics of the SQL trim function.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>LENGTH</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Returns the length of a string.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>LOCATE</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Locates a string within another string.
                            </para>
                            <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/locate_bnf.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                            <para>
                                The third argument (optional) is used to denote a position from which to start looking.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>ABS</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Calculates the mathematical absolute value of a numeric value.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>MOD</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Calculates the remainder of dividing the first argument by the second.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>SQRT</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Calculates the mathematical square root of a numeric value.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>CURRENT_DATE</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Returns the database current date.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>CURRENT_TIME</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Returns the database current time.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>CURRENT_TIMESTAMP</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Returns the database current timestamp.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Standardized functions - HQL</title>
                <para>
                    Beyond the JPQL standardized functions, HQL makes some additional functions available regardless
                    of the underlying database in use.
                </para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>BIT_LENGTH</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Returns the length of binary data.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>CAST</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Performs a SQL cast.  The cast target should name the Hibernate mapping type to use.
                                See the chapter on data types for more information.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>EXTRACT</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Performs a SQL extraction on datetime values.  An extraction extracts parts of
                                the datetime (the year, for example).  See the abbreviated forms below.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>SECOND</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Abbreviated extract form for extracting the second.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>MINUTE</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Abbreviated extract form for extracting the minute.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>HOUR</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Abbreviated extract form for extracting the hour.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>DAY</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Abbreviated extract form for extracting the day.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>MONTH</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Abbreviated extract form for extracting the month.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>YEAR</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Abbreviated extract form for extracting the year.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>STR</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Abbreviated form for casting a value as character data.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Non-standardized functions</title>
                <para>
                    Hibernate Dialects can register additional functions known to be available for that particular
                    database product.  These functions are also available in HQL (and JPQL, though only when using
                    Hibernate as the JPA provider obviously).  However, they would only be available when using that
                    database/Dialect.  Applications that aim for database portability should avoid using functions
                    in this category.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Application developers can also supply their own set of functions.  This would usually represent
                    either custom SQL functions or aliases for snippets of SQL.  Such function declarations are
                    made by using the <methodname>addSqlFunction</methodname> method of
                    <classname>org.hibernate.cfg.Configuration</classname>
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section id="ql-collection-expressions">
            <title>Collection-related expressions</title>
            <para>
                There are a few specialized expressions for working with collection-valued associations.  Generally
                these are just abbreviated forms or other expressions for the sake of conciseness.
            </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>SIZE</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Calculate the size of a collection.  Equates to a subquery!
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>MAXELEMENT</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Available for use on collections of basic type.  Refers to the maximum value as determined
                            by applying the <literal>max</literal> SQL aggregation.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>MAXINDEX</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Available for use on indexed collections.  Refers to the maximum index (key/position) as
                            determined by applying the <literal>max</literal> SQL aggregation.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>MINELEMENT</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Available for use on collections of basic type.  Refers to the minimum value as determined
                            by applying the <literal>min</literal> SQL aggregation.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>MININDEX</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Available for use on indexed collections.  Refers to the minimum index (key/position) as
                            determined by applying the <literal>min</literal> SQL aggregation.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>ELEMENTS</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Used to refer to the elements of a collection as a whole.  Only allowed in the where clause.
                            Often used in conjunction with <literal>ALL</literal>, <literal>ANY</literal> or
                            <literal>SOME</literal> restrictions.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>INDICES</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Similar to <literal>elements</literal> except that <literal>indices</literal> refers to
                            the collections indices (keys/positions) as a whole.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <example>
                <title>Collection-related expressions examples</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/collection_expression_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                Elements of indexed collections (arrays, lists, and maps) can be referred to by index operator.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Index operator examples</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/index_operator_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                See also <xref linkend="ql-collection-qualification"/> as there is a good deal of overlap.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="ql-entity-type-exp">
            <title>Entity type</title>
            <para>
                We can also refer to the type of an entity as an expression.  This is mainly useful when dealing
                with entity inheritance hierarchies.  The type can expressed using a <literal>TYPE</literal> function
                used to refer to the type of an identification variable representing an entity.  The name of the
                entity also serves as a way to refer to an entity type.  Additionally the entity type can be
                parametrized, in which case the entity's Java Class reference would be bound as the parameter
                value.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Entity type expression examples</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/entity_type_exp_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                HQL also has a legacy form of referring to an entity type, though that legacy form is considered
                deprecated in favor of <literal>TYPE</literal>.  The legacy form would have used <literal>p.class</literal>
                in the examples rather than <literal>type(p)</literal>.  It is mentioned only for completeness.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>CASE expressions</title>
            <para>
                Both the simple and searched forms are supported, as well as the 2 SQL defined abbreviated forms
                (<literal>NULLIF</literal> and <literal>COALESCE</literal>)
            </para>
            <section>
                <title>Simple CASE expressions</title>
                <para>
                    The simple form has the following syntax:
                </para>
                <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/simple_case_bnf.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                <example>
                    <title>Simple case expression example</title>
                    <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/simple_case_exp_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                </example>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Searched CASE expressions</title>
                <para>
                    The searched form has the following syntax:
                </para>
                <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/searched_case_bnf.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                <example>
                    <title>Searched case expression example</title>
                    <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/searched_case_exp_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                </example>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>NULLIF expressions</title>
                <para>
                    NULLIF is an abbreviated CASE expression that returns NULL if its operands are considered equal.
                </para>
                <example>
                    <title>NULLIF example</title>
                    <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/nullif_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                </example>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>COALESCE expressions</title>
                <para>
                    COALESCE is an  abbreviated CASE expression that returns the first non-null operand.  We have seen a 
                    number of COALESCE examples above.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="ql-select-clause">
        <title>The <literal>SELECT</literal> clause</title>
        <para>
            The <literal>SELECT</literal> clause identifies which objects and values to return as the query results.
            The expressions discussed in <xref linkend="ql-expressions"/> are all valid select expressions, except
            where otherwise noted.  See the section <xref linkend="ql-api"/> for information on handling the results
            depending on the types of values specified in the <literal>SELECT</literal> clause.
        </para>

        <para>
            There is a particular expression type that is only valid in the select clause.  Hibernate calls this
            <quote>dynamic instantiation</quote>.  JPQL supports some of that feature and calls it
            a <quote>constructor expression</quote>
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Dynamic instantiation example - constructor</title>
            <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/ctor_dynamic_instantiation_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>
            So rather than dealing with the Object[] (again, see <xref linkend="ql-api"/>) here we are wrapping
            the values in a type-safe java object that will be returned as the results of the query.  The class
            reference must be fully qualified and it must have a matching constructor.
        </para>
        <para>
            The class here need not be mapped.  If it does represent an entity, the resulting instances are
            returned in the NEW state (not managed!).
        </para>

        <para>
            That is the part JPQL supports as well.  HQL supports additional <quote>dynamic instantiation</quote>
            features.  First, the query can specify to return a List rather than an Object[] for scalar results:
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>Dynamic instantiation example - list</title>
            <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/list_dynamic_instantiation_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
            The results from this query will be a <![CDATA[List<List>]]> as opposed to a <![CDATA[List<Object[]>]]>
        </para>

        <para>
            HQL also supports wrapping the scalar results in a Map.
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>Dynamic instantiation example - map</title>
            <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/map_dynamic_instantiation_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
            The results from this query will be a <![CDATA[List<Map<String,Object>>]]> as opposed to a
            <![CDATA[List<Object[]>]]>.  The keys of the map are defined by the aliases given to the select
            expressions.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="ql-conditional-expressions">
        <title>Predicates</title>
        <para>
            Predicates form the basis of the where clause, the having clause and searched case expressions.
            They are expressions which resolve to a truth value, generally <literal>TRUE</literal> or
            <literal>FALSE</literal>, although boolean comparisons involving NULLs generally resolve to
            <literal>UNKNOWN</literal>.
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>Relational comparisons</title>
            <para>
                Comparisons involve one of the comparison operators - <![CDATA[=, >, >=, <, <=, <>]>.  HQL also defines
                <![CDATA[!=]]> as a comparison operator synonymous with <![CDATA[<>]]>.  The operands should be
                of the same type.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Relational comparison examples</title>
                <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/predicate_comparison_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                Comparisons can also involve subquery qualifiers - <literal>ALL</literal>, <literal>ANY</literal>,
                <literal>SOME</literal>.  SOME and ANY are synonymous.
            </para>
            <para>
                The ALL qualifier resolves to true if the comparison is true for all of the values in the result of
                the subquery.  It resolves to false if the subquery result is empty.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>ALL subquery comparison qualifier example</title>
                <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/predicate_comparison_example_using_all.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                The ANY/SOME qualifier resolves to true if the comparison is true for some of (at least one of) the
                values in the result of the subquery.  It resolves to false if the subquery result is empty.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Nullness predicate</title>
            <para>
                Check a value for nullness.  Can be applied to basic attribute references, entity references and
                parameters.  HQL additionally allows it to be applied to component/embeddable types.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Nullness checking examples</title>
                <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/predicate_nullness_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Like predicate</title>
            <para>
                Performs a like comparison on string values.  The syntax is:
            </para>
            <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/predicate_like_bnf.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <para>
                The semantics follow that of the SQL like expression.  The <literal>pattern_value</literal> is the
                pattern to attempt to match in the <literal>string_expression</literal>.  Just like SQL,
                <literal>pattern_value</literal> can use <quote>_</quote> and <quote>%</quote> as wildcards.  The
                meanings are the same.  <quote>_</quote> matches any single character.  <quote>%</quote> matches
                any number of characters.
            </para>
            <para>
                The optional <literal>escape_character</literal> is used to specify an escape character used to
                escape the special meaning of <quote>_</quote> and <quote>%</quote> in the
                <literal>pattern_value</literal>.  THis is useful when needing to search on patterns including either
                <quote>_</quote> or <quote>%</quote>
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Like predicate examples</title>
                <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/predicate_like_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Between predicate</title>
            <para>
                Analogous to the SQL between expression.  Perform a evaluation that a value is within the range
                of 2 other values.  All the operands should have comparable types.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Between predicate examples</title>
                <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/predicate_between_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>In predicate</title>
            <para>
                <literal>IN</literal> predicates performs a check that a particular value is in a list of values.
                Its syntax is:
            </para>
            <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/predicate_in_bnf.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <para>
                The types of the <literal>single_valued_expression</literal> and the individual values in the
                <literal>single_valued_list</literal> must be consistent.    JPQL limits the valid types here
                to string, numeric, date, time, timestamp, and enum types.  In JPQL,
                <literal>single_valued_expression</literal> can only refer to:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <quote>state fields</quote>, which is its term for simple attributes.  Specifically this
                        excludes association and component/embedded attributes.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        entity type expressions.  See <xref linkend="ql-entity-type-exp"/>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
                In HQL, <literal>single_valued_expression</literal> can refer to a far more broad set of expression
                types.  Single-valued association are allowed.  So are component/embedded attributes, although that
                feature depends on the level of support for tuple or <quote>row value constructor syntax</quote> in
                the underlying database.  Additionally, HQL does not limit the value type in any way, though
                application developers should be aware that different types may incur limited support based on
                the underlying database vendor.  This is largely the reason for the JPQL limitations.
            </para>
            <para>
                The list of values can come from a number of different sources.  In the
                <literal>constructor_expression</literal> and <literal>collection_valued_input_parameter</literal>, the
                list of values must not be empty; it must contain at least one value.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>In predicate examples</title>
                <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/predicate_in_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Exists predicate</title>
            <para>
                Exists expressions test the existence of results from a subquery.  The affirmative form returns true
                if the subquery result contains values.  The negated form returns true if the subquery
                result is empty.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Empty collection predicate</title>
            <para>
                The <literal>IS [NOT] EMPTY</literal> expression applies to collection-valued path expressions.  It
                checks whether the particular collection has any associated values.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Empty collection expression examples</title>
                <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/empty_collection_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Member-of collection predicate</title>
            <para>
                The <literal>[NOT] MEMBER [OF]</literal> expression applies to collection-valued path expressions.  It
                checks whether a value is a member of the specified collection.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Member-of collection expression examples</title>
                <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/member_of_collection_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>NOT predicate operator</title>
            <para>
                The <literal>NOT</literal> operator is used to negate the predicate that follows it.  If that
                following predicate is true, the NOT resolves to false.  If the predicate is true, NOT resolves to
                false.  If the predicate is unknown, the NOT resolves to unknown as well.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>AND predicate operator</title>
            <para>
                The <literal>AND</literal> operator is used to combine 2 predicate expressions.  The result of the
                AND expression is true if and only if both predicates resolve to true.  If either predicate resolves
                to unknown, the AND expression resolves to unknown as well.  Otherwise, the result is false.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>OR predicate operator</title>
            <para>
                The <literal>OR</literal> operator is used to combine 2 predicate expressions.  The result of the
                OR expression is true if either predicate resolves to true.  If both predicates resolve to unknown, the
                OR expression resolves to unknown.  Otherwise, the result is false.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="ql-where-clause">
        <title>The <literal>WHERE</literal> clause</title>
        <para>
            The <literal>WHERE</literal> clause of a query is made up of predicates which assert whether values in
            each potential row match the predicated checks.  Thus, the where clause restricts the results returned
            from a select query and limits the scope of update and delete queries.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="ql-grouping">
        <title>Grouping</title>
        <para>
            The <literal>GROUP BY</literal> clause allows building aggregated results for various value groups.  As an
            example, consider the following queries:
        </para>
        <example id="group_by_illustration">
            <title>Group-by illustration</title>
            <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/group_by_illustration.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
            The first query retrieves the complete total of all orders.  The second retrieves the total for each
            customer; grouped by each customer.
        </para>
        <para>
            In a grouped query, the where clause applies to the non aggregated values (essentially it determines whether
            rows will make it into the aggregation).  The <literal>HAVING</literal> clause also restricts results,
            but it operates on the aggregated values.  In the <xref linkend="group_by_illustration"/> example,
            we retrieved order totals for all customers.  If that ended up being too much data to deal with,
            we might want to restrict the results to focus only on customers with a summed order total of more than
            $10,000.00:
        </para>
        <example id="having_illustration">
            <title>Having illustration</title>
            <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/having_illustration.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
            The HAVING clause follows the same rules as the WHERE clause and is also made up of predicates.  HAVING is
            applied after the groupings and aggregations have been done; WHERE is applied before.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="ql-ordering">
        <title>Ordering</title>
        <para>
            The results of the query can also be ordered.  The <literal>ORDER BY</literal> clause is used to specify
            the selected values to be used to order the result.  The types of expressions considered valid as part
             of the order-by clause include:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    state fields
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    component/embeddable attributes
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    scalar expressions such as arithmetic operations, functions, etc.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    identification variable declared in the select clause for any of the previous expression types
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            Additionally, JPQL says that all values referenced in the order-by clause must be named in the select
            clause.  HQL does not mandate that restriction, but applications desiring database portability should be
            aware that not all databases support referencing values in the order-by clause that are not referenced
            in the select clause.
        </para>
        <para>
            Individual expressions in the order-by can be qualified with either <literal>ASC</literal> (ascending) or
            <literal>DESC</literal> (descending) to indicated the desired ordering direction. Null values can be placed
            in front or at the end of sorted set using <literal>NULLS FIRST</literal> or <literal>NULLS LAST</literal>
            clause respectively.
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>Order-by examples</title>
            <programlisting><xi:include href="extras/order_by_example.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
    </section>

    <section id="ql-api">
        <title>Query API</title>
    </section>
</chapter>
