<chapter id="filters">
    <title>Filtering data</title>
    
    <para>
        Hibernate3 provides an innovative new approach to handling data with "visibility" rules.
        A <emphasis>Hibernate filter</emphasis> is a global, named, parameterized filter that may be 
        enabled or disabled for a particular Hibernate session.
    </para>

    <sect1 id="objectstate-filters" revision="1">
        <title>Hibernate filters</title>

        <para>
            Hibernate3 adds the ability to pre-define filter criteria and attach those filters at both
            a class and a collection level. A filter criteria is the ability to define a restriction clause
            very similiar to the existing "where" attribute available on the class and various collection
            elements. Except these filter conditions can be parameterized. The application can then make
            the decision at runtime whether given filters should be enabled and what their parameter
            values should be. Filters can be used like database views, but parameterized inside the
            application.
        </para>

        <para>
            In order to use filters, they must first be defined and then attached to the appropriate
            mapping elements. To define a filter, use the <literal>&lt;filter-def/&gt;</literal> element
            within a <literal>&lt;hibernate-mapping/&gt;</literal> element:
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[<filter-def name="myFilter">
    <filter-param name="myFilterParam" type="string"/>
</filter-def>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            Then, this filter can be attached to a class:
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[<class name="myClass" ...>
    ...
    <filter name="myFilter" condition=":myFilterParam = MY_FILTERED_COLUMN"/>
</class>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            or, to a collection:
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[<set ...>
    <filter name="myFilter" condition=":myFilterParam = MY_FILTERED_COLUMN"/>
</set>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            or, even to both (or multiples of each) at the same time.
        </para>

        <para>
            The methods on <literal>Session</literal> are: <literal>enableFilter(String filterName)</literal>,
            <literal>getEnabledFilter(String filterName)</literal>, and <literal>disableFilter(String filterName)</literal>.
            By default, filters are <emphasis>not</emphasis> enabled for a given session; they must be explcitly
            enabled through use of the <literal>Session.enabledFilter()</literal> method, which returns an
            instance of the <literal>Filter</literal> interface. Using the simple filter defined above, this
            would look like:
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[session.enableFilter("myFilter").setParameter("myFilterParam", "some-value");]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            Note that methods on the org.hibernate.Filter interface do allow the method-chaining common to much of Hibernate.
        </para>

        <para>
            A full example, using temporal data with an effective record date pattern:
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[<filter-def name="effectiveDate">
    <filter-param name="asOfDate" type="date"/>
</filter-def>

<class name="Employee" ...>
...
    <many-to-one name="department" column="dept_id" class="Department"/>
    <property name="effectiveStartDate" type="date" column="eff_start_dt"/>
    <property name="effectiveEndDate" type="date" column="eff_end_dt"/>
...
    <!--
        Note that this assumes non-terminal records have an eff_end_dt set to
        a max db date for simplicity-sake
    -->
    <filter name="effectiveDate"
            condition=":asOfDate BETWEEN eff_start_dt and eff_end_dt"/>
</class>

<class name="Department" ...>
...
    <set name="employees" lazy="true">
        <key column="dept_id"/>
        <one-to-many class="Employee"/>
        <filter name="effectiveDate"
                condition=":asOfDate BETWEEN eff_start_dt and eff_end_dt"/>
    </set>
</class>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            Then, in order to ensure that you always get back currently effective records, simply
            enable the filter on the session prior to retrieving employee data:
        </para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[Session session = ...;
session.enabledFilter("effectiveDate").setParameter("asOfDate", new Date());
List results = session.createQuery("from Employee as e where e.salary > :targetSalary")
         .setLong("targetSalary", new Long(1000000))
         .list();
]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            In the HQL above, even though we only explicitly mentioned a salary constraint on the results,
            because of the enabled filter the query will return only currently active employees who have
            a salary greater than a million dollars.
        </para>

        <para>
            Note: if you plan on using filters with outer joining (either through HQL or load fetching) be
            careful of the direction of the condition expression.  Its safest to set this up for left
            outer joining; in general, place the parameter first followed by the column name(s) after
            the operator.
        </para>

        <para>
            After being defined a filter might be attached to multiple entities and/or
            collections each with its own condition.  That can be tedious when the
            conditions are the same each time.  Thus <literal>&lt;filter-def/&gt;</literal>
            allows defining a default condition, either as an attribute or CDATA:
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[<filter-def name="myFilter" condition="abc > xyz">...</filter-def>
<filter-def name="myOtherFilter">abc=xyz</filter-def>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            This default condition will then be used whenever the filter is attached to something
            without specifying a condition.  Note that this means you can give a specific condition
            as part of the attachment of the filter which overrides the default condition in that
            particular case.
        </para>

    </sect1>

</chapter>

