<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>

<!--
  ~ Hibernate, Relational Persistence for Idiomatic Java
  ~
  ~ License: GNU Lesser General Public License (LGPL), version 2.1 or later.
  ~ See the lgpl.txt file in the root directory or <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl-2.1.html>.
  -->
<chapter xml:id="pc"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <info>
        <title>Persistence Contexts</title>
    </info>

    <para>
        Both the <interfacename>org.hibernate.Session</interfacename> API and
        <interfacename>javax.persistence.EntityManager</interfacename> API represent a context for dealing with
        persistent data.  This concept is called a <literal>persistence context</literal>.  Persistent data has a
        state in relation to both a persistence context and the underlying database.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
        <title>Entity states</title>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                <literal>transient</literal> - the entity has just been instantiated and is
                not associated with a persistence context.  It has no persistent representation in the database and
                typically no identifier value has been assigned.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                <literal>managed</literal>, or <literal>persistent</literal> - the entity has an associated identifier
                and is associated with a persistence context.  It may or may not physically exist in the database
                yet.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                <literal>detached</literal> - the entity has an associated identifier, but is no longer associated with
                a persistence context (usually because the persistence context was closed or the instance was evicted
                from the context)
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                <literal>removed</literal> - the entity has an associated identifier and is associated with a persistence
                context, however it is scheduled for removal from the database.
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
        Much of the <interfacename>org.hibernate.Session</interfacename> and
        <interfacename>javax.persistence.EntityManager</interfacename> methods deal with moving entities between these
        states.
    </para>


    <section>
        <title>Making entities persistent</title>

        <para>
            Once you've created a new entity instance (using the standard <literal>new</literal> operator) it is in
            <literal>new</literal> state.   You can make it persistent by associating it to either a
            <interfacename>org.hibernate.Session</interfacename> or
            <interfacename>javax.persistence.EntityManager</interfacename>
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Example of making an entity persistent</title>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/MakingPersistentWithSession.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/MakingPersistentWithEM.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>
            <interfacename>org.hibernate.Session</interfacename> also has a method named <methodname>persist</methodname>
            which follows the exact semantic defined in the JPA specification for the <methodname>persist</methodname>
            method.  It is this method on <interfacename>org.hibernate.Session</interfacename> to which the
            Hibernate <interfacename>javax.persistence.EntityManager</interfacename> implementation delegates.
        </para>

        <para>
            If the <classname>DomesticCat</classname> entity type has a generated identifier, the value is associated
            to the instance when the <methodname>save</methodname> or <methodname>persist</methodname> is called.  If the
            identifier is not automatically generated, the application-assigned (usually natural) key value has to be
            set on the instance before <methodname>save</methodname> or <methodname>persist</methodname> is called.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Deleting entities</title>
        <para>
            Entities can also be deleted.
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>Example of deleting an entity</title>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/DeletingWithSession.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/DeletingWithEM.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
            It is important to note that Hibernate itself can handle deleting detached state.  JPA, however, disallows
            it.  The implication here is that the entity instance passed to the
            <interfacename>org.hibernate.Session</interfacename> <methodname>delete</methodname> method can be either
            in managed or detached state, while the entity instance passed to <methodname>remove</methodname> on
            <interfacename>javax.persistence.EntityManager</interfacename> must be in managed state.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Obtain an entity reference without initializing its data</title>
        <para>
            Sometimes referred to as lazy loading, the ability to obtain a reference to an entity without having to
            load its data is hugely important.  The most common case being the need to create an association between
            an entity and another, existing entity.
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>Example of obtaining an entity reference without initializing its data</title>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/GetReferenceWithSession.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/GetReferenceWithEM.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
            The above works on the assumption that the entity is defined to allow lazy loading, generally through
            use of runtime proxies.  For more information see <xref linkend="devguide-mappingEntities"/>.  In both
            cases an exception will be thrown later if the given entity does not refer to actual database state if and
            when the application attempts to use the returned proxy in any way that requires access to its data.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Obtain an entity with its data initialized</title>

        <para>
            It is also quite common to want to obtain an entity along with with its data, for display for example.
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>Example of obtaining an entity reference with its data initialized</title>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/LoadWithSession.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/LoadWithEM.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
            In both cases null is returned if no matching database row was found.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Obtain an entity by natural-id</title>

        <para>
            In addition to allowing to load by identifier, Hibernate allows applications to load by declared
            natural identifier.
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>Example of simple natural-id access</title>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/SimpleNaturalIdLoading.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <example>
            <title>Example of natural-id access</title>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/NaturalIdLoading.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
            Just like we saw above, access entity data by natural id allows both the <methodname>load</methodname>
            and <methodname>getReference</methodname> forms, with the same semantics.
        </para>

        <para>
            Accessing persistent data by identifier and by natural-id is consistent in the Hibernate API.  Each defines
            the same 2 data access methods:
        </para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><methodname>getReference</methodname></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Should be used in cases where the identifier is assumed to exist, where non-existence would be
                        an actual error.  Should never be used to test existence.  That is because this method will
                        prefer to create and return a proxy if the data is not already associated with the Session
                        rather than hit the database.  The quintessential use-case for using this method is to create
                        foreign-key based associations.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><methodname>load</methodname></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Will return the persistent data associated with the given identifier value or null if that
                        identifier does not exist.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para>
            In addition to those 2 methods, each also defines the method <methodname>with</methodname> accepting
            a <interfacename>org.hibernate.LockOptions</interfacename> argument.  Locking is discussed in a separate
            chapter.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Refresh entity state</title>

        <para>
            You can reload an entity instance and it's collections at any time.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Example of refreshing entity state</title>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/RefreshWithSession.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/RefreshWithEM.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>
            One case where this is useful is when it is known that the database state has changed since the data was
            read.  Refreshing allows the current database state to be pulled into the entity instance and the
            persistence context.
        </para>

        <para>
            Another case where this might be useful is when database triggers are used to initialize some of the
            properties of the entity.  Note that only the entity instance and its collections are refreshed unless you
            specify <literal>REFRESH</literal> as a cascade style of any associations.  However, please note that
            Hibernate has the capability to handle this automatically through its notion of generated properties.
            See the discussion of non-identifier generated attributes in the
            <citetitle>Hibernate User Guide</citetitle>
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Modifying managed/persistent state</title>

        <para>
            Entities in managed/persistent state may be manipulated by the application and any changes will be
            automatically detected and persisted when the persistence context is flushed. There is no need to call a
            particular method to make your modifications persistent.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Example of modifying managed state</title>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/ManagedUpdateWithSession.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/ManagedUpdateWithEM.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Working with detached data</title>

        <para>
            Detachment is the process of working with data outside the scope of any persistence context.  Data becomes
            detached in a number of ways.  Once the persistence context is closed, all data that was associated with it
            becomes detached.  Clearing the persistence context has the same effect.  Evicting a particular entity
            from the persistence context makes it detached.  And finally, serialization will make the deserialized form
            be detached (the original instance is still managed).
        </para>

        <para>
            Detached data can still be manipulated, however the persistence context will no longer automatically know
            about these modification and the application will need to intervene to make the changes persistent.
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>Reattaching detached data</title>
            <para>
                Reattachment is the process of taking an incoming entity instance that is in detached state
                and re-associating it with the current persistence context.
            </para>
            <important>
                <para>
                    JPA does not provide for this model.  This is only available through Hibernate
                    <interfacename>org.hibernate.Session</interfacename>.
                </para>
            </important>
            <example>
                <title>Example of reattaching a detached entity</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/ReattachingWithSession1.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/ReattachingWithSession2.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                The method name <methodname>update</methodname> is a bit misleading here.  It does not mean that an
                <literal>SQL</literal> <literal>UPDATE</literal> is immediately performed.  It does, however, mean that
                an <literal>SQL</literal> <literal>UPDATE</literal> will be performed when the persistence context is
                flushed since Hibernate does not know its previous state against which to compare for changes.  Unless
                the entity is mapped with <literal>select-before-update</literal>, in which case Hibernate will
                pull the current state from the database and see if an update is needed.
            </para>
            <para>
                Provided the entity is detached, <methodname>update</methodname> and <methodname>saveOrUpdate</methodname>
                operate exactly the same.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Merging detached data</title>
            <para>
                Merging is the process of taking an incoming entity instance that is in detached state and copying its
                data over onto a new instance that is in managed state.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Visualizing merge</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/VisualizingMerge.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                That is not exactly what happens, but its a good visualization.
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Example of merging a detached entity</title>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/MergeWithSession.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
                <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/MergeWithEM.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            </example>
        </section>

    </section>


    <section>
        <title>Checking persistent state</title>

        <para>
            An application can verify the state of entities and collections in relation to the persistence context.
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>Examples of verifying managed state</title>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/ContainsWithSession.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/ContainsWithEM.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <example>
            <title>Examples of verifying laziness</title>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/CheckingLazinessWithHibernate.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/CheckingLazinessWithJPA.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
            In JPA there is an alternative means to check laziness using the following
            <interfacename>javax.persistence.PersistenceUtil</interfacename> pattern.  However, the
            <interfacename>javax.persistence.PersistenceUnitUtil</interfacename> is recommended where ever possible
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>Alternative JPA means to verify laziness</title>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/CheckingLazinessWithJPA2.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Accessing Hibernate APIs from JPA</title>
        <para>
            JPA defines an incredibly useful method to allow applications access to the APIs of the underlying provider.
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>Usage of EntityManager.unwrap</title>
            <programlisting role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/UnwrapWithEM.java" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
    </section>

    <!-- todo : pull in a distilled version of src/main/docbook/manual/en-US/content/readonly.xml -->

</chapter>
